Manzanar War Relocation Center records, 1942-1946
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Miscellaneous publications and documents re: Japanese Americans during World War II
  - Congressional Record. vol. 89, no. 61-121 (scattered numbers)., April 5 - June 28, 1943.; 19 items. (Box 63)
- Manzanar War Relocation Center - documents
  - Roster of Manzanar residents., June 1, 1942-Dec. 31, 1944; 2 vols. (251 leaves). Typescript (carbon); Including 1 leaf addenda, "admissions since Jan. 1, 1945." Roster marked Nakamura. Nobutaro is on negative microfilm #06630. Also on positive film, in Box 107. (Box 64)
  - Roster of Manzanar residents., Marked Nakamura, Nabutaro. Original material is in Box 64. (Box 107)
  - Western Defense Command. Statistical charts on Japanese population distribution and statistics, on relocation centers, exclusion areas, etc., 1 volume. (Box 64)
  - Certificate of appreciation to Ralph P. Merritt from the Block Managers of the Manzanar Relocation Center., Nov. 27, 1943 (Box 64)
  - 4 graphs showing employment breakdown, birth and death rates at Manzanar., 1942-1944 (Box 64)
  - 1 - 16" × 20" photo of Mrs. Kango Takamura by A.W. Bartel., June 28, 1944 (Box 64)
  - 2 - 14" × 18" display layouts to the Ansel Adams book, Born Free and Equal.. (Box 64)
  - Photostatic copies of WRA "preliminary statistics" on "relocated" Japanese. (Box 68)
  - Civilian Exclusion Orders. Issued by the Western Defense Command and Fourth Army. Presidio of San Francisco, California., March 24, 1942 - July 22, 1942; # 1 - 108 - complete. Broadsides. Includes occasional "Instructions to all persons of Japanese ancestry living in the following area." interfiled with appropriate Exclusion Order. Handbill size copies of all these orders, etc,. are located in the California Ephemera Collection (Collection 200). See "Japanese in California." (Box 74 [portfolio])
- Manzanar Relocation Center - Artwork
  - 1 water color of Manzanar by C.I. Marimoto., 1943 (Box 64)
- Photographs
  - 3 Nisei students at dining table with students and faculty members fromNational Training School in Kansas City, Missouri., March, 1945; 1 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Maeda talking to Lillian Funakubo, a boarder, with Mr. Maeda reading amagazine in their boarding house in Chicago., September, 1944; 2 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Toyone Maeda in his truck in Chicago., September, 1944; 3 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Richard Nishimura caring for Jersey herd at Mapleton Farm in Enosburg Falls, Vermont., August, 1944; 4 (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - Group of Japanese resettlers at Fairmount Park in Philadelphia enjoying refreshments, August, 1944; 5 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - Jack Hirose, a commercial artist, working in the Art Dept. of the WashingtonPost in Washington, D.C., February, 1944; 6 (Box 65, Folder 6)
  - About 100 Issei and Nisei lay flowers on graves of dead Japanese ancestry at Evergreen Cemetery in Los Angeles on Memorial Day, May, 1945; 7 (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Hal Takaoka, a floral designer in Peoria, Illinois, March, 1945; 8 (Box 65, Folder 8)
  - Paul M. Nakamoto, a maintenance man at the St. Joseph Home, Peoria, Illinois, March, 1945; 9 (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - Ailyn Yasamura, age six, w/classmates in first grade at Horace Mann-Lincoln School in Upper-Manhattan, NY., 10 (Box 65, Folder 10)
  - George Stanicci sketching his wife Margaret at their New York City apartment., July, 1944; 11 (Box 65, Folder 11)
  - Carl Kondo, freelance writer in New York, New York., July, 1944; 12 (Box 65, Folder 12)
  - Akio Nomiyama, Sade Akazawa, and Carl Kondo looking at guide book of New York City., July, 1944; 13 (Box 65, Folder 13)
  - George Nishimura, age 17, working in locker room at Wakonda Country Club in Des Moines, Iowa., June, 1944; 14 (Box 65, Folder 14)
  - Miss Tomiko Yasuda, training as Cadet Nurse at Genesee Hospital in New York, posing with 2 other nurses., 15 (Box 65, Folder 15)
  - Miss Florence Takemura, age 23, working as receptionist at Iowa ChristianWomen's Missionary Society., July, 1944; 16 (Box 65, Folder 16)
  - Ray Komai, layout artist with 2 fellow workers at New York advertising agency., July, 1944; 17 (Box 65, Folder 17)
  - Dr. Frederick R. Thorne discussing with group in New York the cutting and editing of a moving picture taken of several relocation centers., January, 1944; 18 (Box 65, Folder 18)
  - Group of people playing mah jong in a hostel in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania., July, 1944; 19 (Box 65, Folder 19)
  - Kay Kageyama arranging plastic novelties at his business, the New York Plastic Company, with an assistant., March, 1945.; 20 (Box 65, Folder 20)
  - Group of boys playing baseball., 1 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Kay Kageyama arranging plastic novelties at his business, the New York Plastics Company., March, 1945; 2 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Henry and Willy Fukuhara and their father Ichisuke Fukuhara are preparing the beds in one of the Calderone Greenhouses in Farmingdale, Long Island, NY., April, 1945; 3 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Ichisuke Fukuhara with members of their family and friends outside their home on the grounds of the Calderone Greenhouses in Farmingdale, Long Island, New York., April, 1945; 4 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Shizuko Fukuhara, age 4, and her sister Yoshino, age 2, playing w/friends at Farmingdale, Long Island, NY., April, 1945; 5 (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - Saburo Iwana checks in at gate of the American Brass Company in Waterbury, Connecticut., June, 1945; 6 (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - The Kunieda family in front of their home at the greenhouse of Mr. Adolf Sauter, New Jersey., May, 1945; 7 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Katsuo Imakyure, a waiter at Terrace Garden Restaurant at Sulgrave Hotel on Park Avenue in New York., July, 1944; 8 (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - Emiko Ishizanki and Sally Nagasawa with their employer, Robert H. Ransley, a painter, and his wife., July, 1944; 9 (Box 66, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. George Stanicci, a floral designer arranging flowers with a fellow worker in New York., July, 1944.; 10 (Box 66, Folder 10)
  - Mr. and Mrs. George Stanicci having dinner with Carl Kondo and Michael Yonemitsu in New York., July, 1944.; 11 (Box 66, Folder 11)
  - Group of Japanese women who hold civil service jobs in Washington, D.C.., 12 (Box 66, Folder 12)
  - Eva Lee, Mary Suzuki, and Sylvia Levanthal reading newspaper in front of "Americans All" booth at the Pan-Pacific Industrial Exposition in Los Angeles., September, 1944; 13 (Box 66, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors and the Hostel Trustees at the Buddhist Church in San Francisco., July, 1945; 14 (Box 66, Folder 14)
  - Ouye family with friends on front porch of Ouyu home in San Francisco., August, 1945; 15 (Box 66, Folder 15)
  - Group of Nisei men who teach Japanese to officers and men in the Civil Affairs Training School at Stanford University., July, 1945; 16 (Box 66, Folder 16)
  - Group of Nisei women who teach Japanese to Army Officers in the Civil Affairs School at Stanford with Professor A. E. Sokol, July, 1945; 17 (Box 66, Folder 17)
  - Group of Nisei instructors who teach Japanese to army officers at Stanford University, July, 1945; 18 (Box 66, Folder 18)
  - Okamuro and Hara family in the backyard garage of Yam Okamura in Glendale, California., May, 1945; 19 (Box 66, Folder 19)
  - Mr. Iwao Takamoto, an animator at Walt Disney Studios in Hollywood., June, 1945; 20 (Box 66, Folder 20)
  - Yam Okamuro with his family and a friend in the backyard garage of his home in Glendale, California., May, 1945; 21 (Box 66, Folder 21)
  - Kiichi Uyeda with Matsuo Yoshida and customers in his store in Little Tokyo in Los Angeles., May, 1945; 22 (Box 66, Folder 22)
  - Buddhist Hostel in Los Angeles near USC with 2 men standing in front talking., June, 1945; 1 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Takaki Grocery on Normandie in Los Angeles with man and woman looking through food stands., June, 1945; 2 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Michiko Kataoka and Meriko Hoshiyama with 2 other students sitting in front of Powell Library at UCLA., May, 1945; 3 (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - George Takaki and his father Yoshihiro in their store, Takaki Grocery, with their customers., June, 1945; 4 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - Henry Suenaga and Ben Nishiyama on their beds in the men's dormitories at Evergreen Hostel, Los Angeles., June, 1945; 5 (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - Mr. Takejiro's mansion in the West Adams district of Los Angeles., June, 1945; 6 (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - George Akagi's "boarding house" in West Los Angeles., June, 1946; 7 (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Crowd of people at a Chicago night club listening to a woman sing on stage., January, 1944; 8 (Box 67, Folder 8)
  - Returnees arrive in Los Angeles by bus from Manzanar Relocation Center., May, 1945; 9 (Box 67, Folder 9)
  - 62 (8 x 10) WRA photographs and 2 newspaper clippings., 1943 - 1944; 10 (Box 67, Folder 10)
  - Mary Kitano with 4 other co-workers at the City News Service in Los Angeles., May, 1945; 1 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Tom T. Watanabe, radiologist, in an X-ray laboratory in Chicago., March, 1945; 2 (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Dorothy Tanaka and Toshio Ino in front of a statue at Fairmont Park in Philadelphia., August, 1944; 3 (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - Mr. Suenaga working in a nursery at Hattiesburg, Mississippi., January, 1945; 4; copy 1 of 3. (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Mr. Suenaga working in a nursery at Hattiesburg, Mississippi, January, 1945; 5; copy 2 of 3. (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - Mr. Suenaga working in a nursery at Hattiesburg, Mississippi., January, 1945; 6; copy 3 of 3. (Box 68, Folder 6)
  - Jane Oi and Sally Tsujimoto with Privates Katsuji Nakamoto and Harold Matsumura in Washington, D. C.., 7 (Box 68, Folder 7)
  - Richard Nishimura on a horse-drawn rake on a farm in Enosburg Falls, Vermont, August, 1944; 8 (Box 68, Folder 8)
  - Group of men outside of Bill Mori's K&J Restaurant, their workplace, in Waterbury, Connecticut., August, 1944; 9 (Box 68, Folder 9)
  - Richard Nishimura milking a cow on the Nichols farm in Enosburg Falls, Vermont., August, 1944; 10 (Box 68, Folder 10)
  - Mr. Suenaga and co-worker with shovels at a greenhouse in Hattiesburg, Mississippi., January, 1945; 11 (Box 68, Folder 11)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Toyone Maeda sitting in their living room in Chicago., September, 1944; 12 (Box 68, Folder 12)
  - 2 couples taking a stroll along the Schuylkill River in Fairmount Park in Philadelphia., August, 1944.; 13 (Box 68, Folder 13)
  - 5 Nisei in front of Independence Hall in Philadelphia., August, 1944.; 14 (Box 68, Folder 14)
  - Group of students walking in Royce Quad at UCLA., May, 1945.; 15; copy 1 of 2. (Box 68, Folder 15)
  - Group of students walking in Royce Quad at UCLA., May, 1945.; 16; copy 2 of 2. (Box 68, Folder 16)
  - Sam Kuwahuru cooking at Mr. and Mrs. Haru Tanaka's restaurant in St. Louis, Missouri., March, 1945.; 17 (Box 68, Folder 17)
  - Haru Tanaka cooking in his restaurant in St. Louis, Missouri., March, 1945.; 18 (Box 68, Folder 18)
  - Takako Matsumoto and Ritsuko Nakaji stroll along a street in New York City., July, 1944.; 19 (Box 68, Folder 19)
  - Mrs. George Stanicci arranging flowers, New York., July, 1944.; 20 (Box 68, Folder 20)
  - Sylvia Levanthal, Mary Kitano, Col. H. A. Finch, Eva Lee, and Mary Suzuki atthe "Americans All" booth at the Pan-Pacific Industrial Exposition in Los Angeles., September, 1945.; 1 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - J. S. Takeyasu standing in a flower field on his land in San Fernando, California., September, 1945.; 2 (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - Mr. Kitazawa at his nursery in San Jose, California., July, 1945.; 3 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - Kiyo Kitazawa working in her garden in San Jose, California., July, 1945.; 4 (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - Mr. Kobayashi and his son, Richard, taking a break from working in their vineyard in Florin, California., August, 1945.; 5 (Box 69, Folder 5)
  - Richard Kobayashi getting a drink from the well in the family's vineyard inFlorin, Califonia., September, 1945.; 6 (Box 69, Folder 6)
  - Toshio Ino, Fuku Yokoyama, and Dorothy Tanaka standing at the steps of the Philadelphia Art Museum., August, 1944.; 7 (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - Eva Lee and Mary Suzuki with photographs at the Pan-Pacific Industrial Exposition., September, 1945.; 8 (Box 69, Folder 8)
  - The Shimokawa family with Reverand S. Kowta walking toward the Evergreen Hostel., June, 1945.; 9 (Box 69, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Mary Kito in a "Now" magazine office in Los Angeles with Malcolm Thurburn and Nob Sawamura., May, 1945.; 10 (Box 69, Folder 10)
  - Two female and two male Nisei teachers standing in front of a building on the Stanford campus., July, 1945.; 11 (Box 69, Folder 11)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Toyone Maeda on the front steps of their boarding house in Chicago with 3 of their tenants in front of them., September, 1944.; 12 (Box 69, Folder 12)
  - Emiko Ishiski, an assistant to the artist Robert H. Ransley, decorating a goblet., July, 1944.; 13 (Box 69, Folder 13)
  - Betty Lyou, holding a newspaper, with her husband Rodney Voight, Fusako Takemoto and Mary Kitano in an office of the City News Service in Los Angeles., 14 (Box 69, Folder 14)
  - Shizuka Furuto sitting at a desk in her apartment in Des Moines, Iowa., July, 1944.; 15 (Box 69, Folder 15)
  - Jackson and Mary Takayanagi in their apartment in Des Moines, Iowa., July, 1944.; 16 (Box 69, Folder 16)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Tomatsu Gorai and Mr. Ushimatsu Kubota looking at the job bulletin board in the Philadelphia WRA office., July, 1945.; 17 (Box 69, Folder 17)
  - Percy Fukushima, shipping clerk at James G. Biddle Company., July, 1944.; 18 (Box 69, Folder 18)
  - Katsuo Imakyure, a waiter at Terrace Garden in Sulgrave Hotel in New York City., July, 1944.; 19 (Box 69, Folder 19)
  - Shisuo Mitsuhata, chef at Clifton's Cafeteria in Los Angeles., June, 1945.; 20 (Box 69, Folder 20)
  - R. Nojima taking care of the plants on the land of Mr. Takeyasu in San Fernando, California., September, 1945.; 21 (Box 69, Folder 21)